Register of the Vasilii Maklakov Papers, 1881-1956
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject File, 1881-1956
  - Ligue pour la Regeneration de la Russie en Union avec les Allies, 1918. Miscellaneous material, including writings of Lieut.-Gen. E. Miller (Folder 13)
  - Miliukov, Pavel. See also Correspondence FILE/Pavel Miliukov
    - Clippings. Includes articles by or about P. Miliukov and V. Maklakov
      - Novoe Russkoe Slovo, 1953 (Folder 14)
      - Posledniia Novosti
        - Undated (Folder 15)
        - 1929 (Folder 16-17)
        - 1930 (Folder 18)
        - 1931 (Folder 19)
        - 1934 (Folder 20)
        - 1936 (Folder 21)
        - 1937 (Folder 22)
        - 1939 (Folder 23)
      - Vozrozhdenie, 1930's (Folder 24)
  - Ob"edinenie Russkoi Emigratsii dlia sblizheniia s Sovetskoi Rossieii
    - Correspondence, 1944-1945
      - General
        - Undated (Folder 24)
        - 1944 (Folder 26)
        - 1945 (Folder 27)
      - Ermakov, Mstislav (Folder 28)
      - Makhrov, Pavel, Gen. Includes material on Makhrov address re "Soiuz sovetskikh patriotov" (Folder 29)
      - Rogovskii, Evgenii (Folder 30)
      - Shatilov, Pavel, Lieut.-Gen. (Folder 31)
      - Stakhov, Aleksandr (Folder 32)
      - Stupnitskii, Arsenii (Folder 33)
      - Tatarinov, V. (Folder 34)
      - Verderevskii, P. (Folder 35)
      - Vilechkovskii, Kirill (Folder 36)
    - List of members, n.d. (Box 20., Folder 1)
    - Printed matter
      - General. Al'perin, Abram, 1945 March. "Doklad". Brochure (Folder 2)
      - Clippings. Includes "Sovetskaia vlast' i emigratsiia" and other writings by V. Maklakov (Folder 3)
    - Protocols of meetings, 1945 May and December (Folder 4)
    - Reports and other writings. Typescript
      - Relationship between Russian emigration and the Soviet State, undated. Includes writings by V. Maklakov (Folder 5-6)
      - Visit of Ob"edinenie representatives to Soviet ambassador Bogomolov, 1945 February (Folder 7)
    - Statutes in French translation, Union des Emigres Russes pour le Rapprochement avec la Russie Sovietique. Typescript (Folder 8)
  - Rodichev, F. See also Correspondence File/F. Rodichev and A. Rodicheva Biographical material
    - Autobiography, 1932. Includes correspondence with A. Lednitskii (Folder 9)
    - "The Liberal Movement in Russia (1891-1905)", The Slavonic Review, 1923 June. Printed copy (Folder 10)
    - Obituaries, 1933. Typescript (Folder 11)
    - Clippings, 1922 (Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, speeches and biographical material re Rodichev and Gertsen families, 1881-1928. Typescript copies (Folder 13)
    - Speeches delivered in Duma
      - 1907 November 17. Handwritten copy (Folder 14)
      - 1917 April 27. Rech', 1917, April 29. Printed copy (Folder 15)
    - Writings
      - Pervaia rech' Imperatora Nikolaia II, 1895. Typescript copy of brochure (Folder 16)
      - "K pol'skomu voprosu", 1905 March 20. Handwritten copy of article published in Pravo (Folder 17)
  - Russian Embassy in Paris
    - Economic and financial matters
      - General
        - Correspondence and reports. Franco-Russian financial relations, 1917 (Folder 18)
        - Reports. Typescript
          - General, 1917-1922 (Folder 19)
          - Holmstrem, Vladimir, 1921 (Folder 20)
          - Martens, (?), 1918 (Folder 21)
      - Comite des Representants des Banques Russes a Paris
        - Printed matter
          - Memoires elabores a l'occasion de la Conference de Genes, 1922 April (Folder 22)
          - Memoires elabores a l'occasion de la Conference de La Haye, 1922 June (Folder 23)
        - Report, 1923 November. Typescript (Folder 24)
    - Franco-Russian relations
      - Printed matter. Bulletin d'informations russes and other bulletins, 1921-1923 Reports. Typescript (Folder 25)
        - General, n.d. (Folder 26)
        - Berthelot, M., Capt. "Compte rendu d'une mission executee aupres du General Denikine..." 1919 (Folder 27)
        - Ministere des Affaires Etrangeres. "Proces-verbal de la reunion...entre les Generaux Denikine et Berthelot", 1919 (Folder 28)
    - Intelligence, 1917. Typescript reports (Folder 29)
    - Miscellany, 1917-1923 (Folder 30)
  - Russkaia Mysl' (Box 21.)
    - Clippings, 1949 (Folder 1)
    - Correspondence of Vasilii Maklakov
      - Editorial Board, 1949-1951. Includes letter of Abram Al'perin and others (Folder 2)
      - IAblonskii, Sergei, 1949 (Folder 3)
      - Kovalevskii, Petr, 1955-1956 (Folder 4)
      - Lazarevskii, Vladimir, 1949 (Folder 5)
      - Polianskii, Vasilii, 1949 (Folder 6)
      - Stefanovskii, Stepan, 1949 (Folder 7)
  - Russkii Evakuatsionnyi Komitet v Pol'she. See also Correspondence/Dimitrii Filosofov and Boris Savinkov Correspondence
    - General, with French and Polish authorities, 1921 February-October. Typescript copies (Folder 8)
    - Miller, Evgenii, Lieut.-Gen., 1921 (Folder 9)
    - Party program, 1923 June (Folder 10)
    - Printed matter, n.d.
      - "Iiun' 1920-Noiabr' 1921" (Folder 11)
      - "Open Letter to the Right Hon. David Lloyd George from Boris Savinkov" (Folder 12)
    - Protocols and minutes of meetings, 1921 July-August. Mimeograph (Folder 13)
    - Reports
      - General, April-August. Activities of B. Savinkov and Russo-Polish relations. Typescript (Folder 14-16)
      - Author unknown. Report to V. Maklakov, 1921 (Folder 17)
  - Trubetskoi, Petr, Prince. See also Correspondence/Trubetskoi, Nikita and Vladimir, Princes
    - Biographical material, n.d. Typescript (Folder 18)
    - Reminiscenses of Princess O. Trubetskaia. Excerpts from diaries, n.d. Typescript (Folder 19)
    - Writings. Minority address by the Moscow nobility to Emperor Nicholas II and letter to the Interior Minister, 1905. Typescript (Folder 20)
  - Vinaver, Mikhail
    - Obituary. Gippius, Z. Zveno, 1926. Printed copy (Folder 21)
    - Review of Vinaver, Nedavnee. Vospominaniia i kharakteristiki, n.d. Author unknown. Typescript (Folder 22)
  - World War I. Prisoners of War. The Hague Conference. (Folder 23)
  - Internatinal Red Cross, 1916. Bound typescript documents
  - World War II and the Russian emigration in France (Box 22.)
    - General
      - Addresses by emigre individuals and organizations to compatriots, 1941-1946. Typescript
        - General (Folder 1)
        - Repatriation of former Soviet citizens (Folder 2)
      - Official correspondence with French officials and German occupation authorities, 1940-1946
        - General. Typescript and handwritten
          - Undated. Includes Maklakov letter re relics of Russian Imperial family kept in Paris embassy (Folder 3)
          - 1940 (Folder 4)
          - 1941
            - January-May (Folder 5)
            - June-December (Folder 6)
          - 1942 (Folder 7)
          - 1943-1946 (Folder 8)
        - Russian nationals arrested by German authorities, 1941
          - General. Includes letters from camp in Compiegne and list of those arrested. Typescript (Folder 9)
          - Gershuni, Boris (Folder 10)
          - Krasinskii, Prince (Folder 11)
      - Printed matter
        - Emigre newspapers, 1941 (Folder 12)
        - Newsletter. Russkii Patriot, 1944. Mimeograph (Folder 13)
      - Registration forms required by occupation police, 1941. Typescript samples (Folder 14)
      - Writings re political situation of emigre community, 1940-1941. Typescript. Includes Lieut.-Gen. Denikin (Folder 15)
    - Comite d'Entreaide des Emigres Russes (Modrach Committee), 1941. Propaganda leaflets. Printed copies. See also General/Correspondence with French and German authorities (Folder 16)
    - Groupe d'Action des Emigres Russes, 1944. Miscellaneous material. Typescript and printed matter (Folder 17)
    - Office Central des Refugies Russes. See General/Correspondence with French and German authorities
    - Union des Patriotes Russes, 1944. Correspondence and statutes. Typescript (Folder 18)
    - Union des Patriotes Sovietiques, 1946. Correspondence (Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous writings
    - General, 1936. Typescript (Folder 20)
    - Aleksinskii, Grigorii, Les Effets economiques et sociaux de la revolution bolcheviste et les causes de son echec, 1920. Printed copy (Folder 21)
    - Denikin, Anton, Lieut.-Gen., "Russkii vopros", 1940. Typescript (Folder 22)
    - Monod-Herzen, Ol'ga, n.d. Handwritten biographical sketch (Folder 23)
    - SHul'gin, V.
      - "Po povodu odnoi stat'i", n.d. Typescript with holograph annotations (Folder 24)
      - Lettre de V. Schoulguine...a M. le Haut-Commissaire pour les affaires des Refugies pres la Societe des Nations, 1929. Printed copy (Folder 25)
- Clippings, 1917-1956
  - General. Includes material by and about V. Maklakov in emigre press, 1922-1956 (Box 23., Folder 1-12)
  - Lists of articles by Russian authors accepted for publication in foreign press, 1921-1922. Typescript (Box 24., Folder 1)
  - Notebooks of clippings
    - Russian press, 1917
      - "Armiia. Revoliutsiia i prikazy Soveta rab. i sold. dep." (Folder 2)
      - "Postanovleniia Vremennago Pravitel'stva" (Folder 3)
      - "Prodovol'stvie" (Folder 4)
      - "Voprosy politiki i rabochii vopros" (Folder 5)
      - "Voprosy voiny" (Folder 6-7)
      - "Zemel'nyi vopros" (Folder 8)
    - European press, 1923. Miscellaneous material related to Soviet Union, arranged by subject. Includes trial of M. Conradi for murder of Soviet ambassador Vorovskii (Box 25., Folder 1-14)
- Oversize File, 1914-1917
  - Album. Iz moego al'boma. SHest'desiat' fotograficheskikh snimkov...Aleksandry Feodotovn y, Izdanie T-va M.O. Vol'f (Box 26.)
  - Cartoon caricatures of German forces
    - General. Lithograph
    - Izdanie ZHurnala "Krivoe Zerkalo", Moscow
  - Flags of Russia and Allies
  - Lubok-style posters and pictures depicting heroic actions of Russian army and civilians
  - Map. "Karta Teatra Voennykh Deistvii v Rossii i Turtsii"
  - Wall-posters, sign-up sheets and miscellany
- Photograph, 1932.
  - Portrait print of F. Rodichev (Photofile Photo File)